<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An instruction to judges &amp; lawyers, that they may act and judge as the judges did of old, and that they may see how they are degenerated from them that judged at the first, and that in reading this thorow, they may see what hath been lost, and how they may be resotored by the power of the Lord ... And how people have bin put to death for that which they should have restored, or been sold for their theft; ... And concerning the poor mans cry, who know his matter and business himself, and is able to speak to it ... Given forth to the intent men might consider these things, and come to the life of God, and live at the first, that justice might run down, and truth and righteousnesse may be set up. G.F.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40203</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826052</idno>
  <idno type="VID">30444</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240892910</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213750</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826052</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99826052e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30444)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1759:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An instruction to judges &amp; lawyers, that they may act and judge as the judges did of old, and that they may see how they are degenerated from them that judged at the first, and that in reading this thorow, they may see what hath been lost, and how they may be resotored by the power of the Lord ... And how people have bin put to death for that which they should have restored, or been sold for their theft; ... And concerning the poor mans cry, who know his matter and business himself, and is able to speak to it ... Given forth to the intent men might consider these things, and come to the life of God, and live at the first, that justice might run down, and truth and righteousnesse may be set up. G.F.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Simmons at the Bull and Mouth neer Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.F. = George Fox.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian ethics --  Anglican authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30444:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30444:1"/>
            <p>AN INSTRUCTION TO JUDGES &amp; LAWYERS,</p>
            <p>That they may act and judge as the Judges did of old, and that they may see how they are degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from them that judged at the first, and that in reading this thorow, they may see what hath been lost, and how they may be restored by the power of the Lord, into that which the Iudges were in at the first, and that without money or reward justice might be done. And how people have bin put to death for that which they should have restored, or been sold for their theft; and how the owners and the thief hath been wronged since the Iudges of old. And also concerning Bills and Writs which hath been the <hi>Form,</hi> but not of <hi>sound words,</hi> they having more in them and charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more upon the people then what is truth, which hath been contrary to the Law, <hi>So say, and and so do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And concerning the poor mans cry, who knows his matter and business himself, and is able to speak to it (according to the Law of Equity which is grounded upon Reason) without hiring a Councellor or an Attorney.</p>
            <p>Given forth to the intent men might consider these things, and come to the life of God, and live as at the first, that Justice might run down, and Truth and Righteousnesse may be set up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the Bull and Mouth neer <hi>Aldersgate.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30444:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30444:2"/>
            <head>Instructions to Judges and Lawyers, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Law came by <hi>Moses,</hi> given forth from God, added because of transgression, which went over all trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressors, which was the higher power, a terrour to the evil doers, a praise to them that do well, not made for the Righteous, but for sinners; and this Law was perfect and endures for ever, according to that of God in every man which is transgressed, which power the soul must be subject to, that is immortall, and all the Lawes among the heathen was called inventions of the heathen which was not received from God.</p>
            <p>The Law of God was, he that smote a man that he died shall be slain for it: if a man lieth not in wait, so that God delivereth him into his hands, then I will appoint him a place whether he shall fly; If a man steal an ox or a sheep and kill it or fell it, he shall restore five Oxen for an Ox, and four sheep for a sheep, and not be hanged for it. Now the Law of God doth not say that a man shall dye for the Ox, or for the Sheep, but restore, and if he have not wherewith, he should be sold for his theft, and he should make full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution. If a man burn another mans field of standing corn, he should make full restitution, and thus the judges was to judge.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Moses</hi> the chief Magistrate had this Law, and for all manner of trespasses, for Oxen, Asses, Sheep, Raiment, lost things which another challenged to be his, both parties should be brought before the Judges, and whom the Judge should condemn, he should pay double to his neighbour, and he should make full restitution; and the King was to give himself to the reading this Law of God, and the Judge was to judge according to it, not for gifts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards which blinded their eyes, for God who is a Judge among Judges, who gave forth his Law, when the Kings
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30444:3"/>&amp; the Judges transgressed his Law, he cast them out among the heathen; and so men and people by the Law of God was not to dye for stealing of cattel or mony, but restore four fold, five fold, or seven fold, or double, this was the Law that was just, or if they had not wherewith, they were to be sold for their theft: here the thief had space to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and here the poor people who had their goods stolen away from them was no loosers, but to hang the thief, he hath no space to repent, and the poor man that hath his goods stolen away may be undone if it be not restored; now if this be not out of all equity, judge you?</p>
            <p>Now the Apostle who Preached Christ the end of the Law said, <hi>Let him that stole steal no more, but labour in the thing that is good,</hi> Now here was the Law among Christians, he did not say hang him, (but gave him space here to repent) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the Law bind the man that lost his goods to be at the charge to prosecute the thief to death and loose his goods both.</p>
            <p>And the Apostle told the Jewes that the Law was good in its place, and was made for murtherers &amp; man-slayers and thieves, &amp;c. and he puts a difference betwixt this, and the Gentiles inventions; now if the Judges in <hi>Israel</hi> should have hanged all for stealing Cattel, or Corn, or Money, or cloathes to the vallue of 13 d. and not the owners have the things stolen restored them again, would not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet have cryed out of them, <hi>their hands were full of blood,</hi> they had cast the Law of God behind their backs, and they had neither mercy nor equity? and God turned them among the heathen that be in the earth, that will destroy a mans life for the creatures, for cloaths, for money; And is not this a proof that whole Christendom which puts men to death for Cloaths, for Oxen, for Asses, that they be out of the Law of God and the Gospel both, among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and worse then the <hi>Jewes?</hi> for life was for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot, burning for burning, wound for wound, stripe for stripe; now this was the Law of Equity, now if they stole other creatures, money, or Oxen, or Sheep, they were to be sold
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30444:3"/>for their theft, and bring seven fold, or four fold, or five fold, or double back to the owner they had stollen from, and if he had it not, he was to be sold for his theft, and not to be hanged for it; And this was the manner of the Judges judgement at the first: Now when the things shall come to be restored as they were at first, and the judges as they were at first, no man should die for Cattel, for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, for goods, the Judges would not hang them, but make all the thieves go to restore to them that they had stollen from, by four fold, or five fold, or seven fold, or double, and make them to make full restitution; if they have not wherewith, to be sold for their theft, then it shall be said that the Judges hands are not full of blood, but that they are restored as they were at first; and thus they must judge without gifts, which hath blinded their eyes, and doth now blind their eyes, without rewards, without respect of persons the rich or the poor, but judge equall judgement; Now how can it be said but that their hands are full of blood; judge. And Kings that thus make a Law, that men shall prosecute men to death that have stollen things from them, or else be guilty of theft, and they lose their goods, and the thiefe lose his life, and have no resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and then they judge for Oxen, for Asses, for Hors<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, for money, for cloaths, to the value of thirteen pence, will put men to death, will hang them, which according to the Law of God should be restored seven fold, or five fold, to those from whom they have stollen, which this would make men beware of stealing, and break down the spirits of men, and if they had not wherewith, to be sold for their theft; for God saith, If a thief be found breaking up, and he be smitten that he die, if the Sun be risen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, there shall be blood shed for him, for he should have made restitution and not taken away his life. Mark that ye Judges how ye differ from them of old, and from the law of God: Now all ye judges that shed the blood of men for their theft, who have not shed mens blood, is not all your blood to be shed for them, and to be required of you by the Lord God in the whole Christendom? and will not God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30444:4"/>come upon you and execute his Law if man should not; for you by the true judgement of the Law should have made them have made full restitution to the owners, not to have taken away their blood, except they had taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ood; but if the thief be found breaking up, and be smirten that he die, there shall be no blood shed for him, if the Sun be not risen upon him. Now hath all the Judges been as at the first, that hath taken away mens lives, and hanged them for stealing of Cattel, goods or mony, corn, Oxen, sheep or cloaths? and have a Law that they should prosecute them to death that the goods were stollen from, and the owners hath had no restitution; and hath taken away the thives life, or that he should be guilty of theft, and the Judge would not let the thief live to restore? Now can any man living in the Law of God, or in Christ the end of the Law the Apostles doctrine uphold such things which saith they must restore four fold, or seven fold, or five fold to the owners; and which saith let him that hath stole steal no more, but labour in the thing that is good? is not this the Scripture, the Law of God, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Doctrine? and them that will kill and hang, and cause others to prosecute to death them that hath stollen Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, money, &amp; goods; and the law saith he shall not die for such things, no blood shed for him; if the thief be killed, and the Sun be risen? Now must not their blood be shed, which causeth blood to be shed? Doth not blood touch blood? Is not blood for blood, wound for wound, stripe for stripe, and life for life for a thief, except it were in the night? and hath not all these judges that have been up, and Kings put men to death, and taken away their blood, and hanged them for stealing Oxen, Asses, Sheep, money, cloathes, robbing houses, since the Judges was not as they were in the beginning, which hath not caused thievs to restore double, four fold, or five, or seven fold; if they have not wherewith, to be sold for their theft; and let him that hath stollen steal no more, but labour in the thing that is good: But first how can he restore four, or five, or seven fold, when ye hang him? or can he be sold
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30444:4"/>for his theft, and so that he might come to repentance? and how can he that hath stole steal no more, and labour in the thing that is honest, and follow the Apostles Doctrine when you hang him? will not here all the righteous Judges rise up in judgement against you, and all the true Apostles and Christians, and judge you to be among the Heathen, and see you to be contrary to the Law and the Gospel? and hath not all these things got up since the Apostacy from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, and the Judges as they were at the first? And hath not all these Judges risen up contrary to that? And is not all these actions practised in the whole Christendom? And must not all these things be restored, as they were in the beginning (which hath been lost) into the right order, and manner of right Judgement, equal and just, righteous and measureable, that the life of the Law should be known, and the equity of it, and the righteousnesse of it, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Doctrine Preached which was the end of it? and should not the Christians live in more mercy then the Law? and do not they live contrary to the Law, worse then the <hi>Jewes</hi> which you used to say were hard-hearted, who takes away mens lives for such things as goods and Cattel? Is not this crueller then the Law, crueller to the thief, crueller to him that the goods were stollen from? are not these the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that do so that are called ravening Wolves? and how can you differ from the Heathen in this, who will kill, hang one another, knock one another on the heads for goods, and earthly things? which was not the Law of God which went over all transgressors and trespasses, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured equally, and was for the subduing of mens wills that acted unequally, and the righteous Judges among men God honoured, and the Kings was to give themselves to the reading of this righteous Law of God; and is not this Law of God cast behind Kings and Judges backs, and Rulers in the whole Christendom? And do you not think you would slay mens thievish natures to let them live and restore four, or five, or seven fold to the owner from whom they stole? or if they had it not, to be sold for their theft? was not this the way to convince them, and to bring them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30444:5"/>but to take away their lives and kill them contrary to the Law, and bid them ask mercy of God, and you give them none, nor the Law, are not you contrary to the Law, cruel? and doth not these actions shew that ye are neither according to the Law of God nor the Gospel, to hang thieves and not let them restore to whom they had stollen from? or if they had not wherewith, to be sold for their theft? and he that stole steal no more, but labour in the thing that is good? Now is not this Law and Gospel? and are not you out of this in the whole Christendom, and found among the Heathen, that will knock men on the head for stealing goods, Cattel, money; and not suffer them to live to make restitution, or to be sold for their theft, to labour in the thing that is good? So are not all your mercies here cruel, and judged with Law and Gospel? So the Lord open your understandings that you may come to see and feel these things in these Ancient of Dayes, in which the Lord is restoring things as they were at the first, and bringing things to passe that hath been past, and letting see what hath been lost, and recovering things as they were at the first, and giving judgement on the contrary; and now shall men be judged according to the Law and Gospel: Therefore now I would have all men to repent every where and do so no more. Let these things that hath been past be sufficient, and ye Judges in the whole Christendom, and Law-makers that makes Laws to take away mens lives for Creatures, hath invented laws of your own contrary to the Law of God, and not made them that men should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store, or be sold for their theft, or steal no more, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in thing that is good, according to the Gospel; and you Judges that hath executed these Lawes, and you Kings that hath made and caused them to be executed, you have not given your selves to the Law of God, but to your own inventions, and acted unrighteously, unmeasurably and unequally; if the blood of all you Judges and Kings should be equally required for all the blood of the thieves, and do ye think it will not be required at your hands who have thus acted contrary to the Law? And you measured by the
<pb facs="tcp:30444:5"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:30444:6"/>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30444:6"/>Just Law of God, and found out of it, which is as you will finde a sharp School-master, and your selves mingled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heathen, who hath taken away the thieves blood and not caused them to make restitution, and so wronged the thief, and wronged the owner they had stollen from; and so wronged your selves, and are Judged by the Law of God: It was said to the Judges they should not do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteously, no unrighteous thing in Judgement, if the Judge had caused him that had goods stollen to prosecute the thief to death, and taken away the thiefs life for goods, and not have made the thief restored and saved his life, they had done unrighteously in judgement, and not righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously; Thou shalt rebuke thy neighbour, and not bear his sin; Now this was the Law, and he did not imprison them that did rebuke these openly in the gates, as the Christians do now; for them that rebuke sin in the gates, rebukes his neighbour, and will not bear his sin; the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates now will cast them into prison, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. You shall keep all my Ordinances; Now do not you all break all the Ordinances of God, and put men to death for that which they should restore, or be sold for their theft? Do not all you Judges and Kings break the Ordinances of God, that kills them, tramples upon them, and casts his Law behind their backs? and doth not this shew how darknesse hath ruled among Judges and Kings of the Earth, since they have not been restored as they were at the first? All you Magistrates and Judges that hath not Judged as they did Judge at the first, and so fallen into the Heathens spirit. And will not the blood of the thieves be upon you all in the whole Christendom, who hath not been as the Judges and chief Magistrates was at the first? but hath taken away the blood of thieves for the creatures, which should have restored double, or four, or seven fold for their theft. You have been contrary all to <hi>Moses</hi> and them that was in the beginning, and destroyed mens lives which you should have saved them to have restored to them which they had wronged, and that was equity, if not, to be sold for their theft until they had paid it; and him that had stole, steal
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30444:7"/>no more, but labour in the thing that is honest, and this is equity, and like law and Gospel; so reform and come into that which doth restore, ye that be in the things that be lost for God is restoring people into things as they was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining who is come to judge: <hi>Solomon</hi> who was a King said <hi>before honour was humility;</hi> Now all Kings, Magistrates &amp; Rulers upon the earth, before they have honour they must have humility; not that which is feigned, but that which is good and pure, not like the fury of <hi>Nabuchadnezer,</hi> not like the brittle Christians that not doffing of the hat will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all Religion, Church and profession; and if they will not give them that; they shall have no justice; now here is buying and selling Justice, not giving them it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they will not give them the hat; Now the hat wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, that honour, that <hi>Idol</hi> is set up by transgressors; But men that be in the Law of God which is over trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, which the Soul must be subject to they mind not the hat, but the Law, to bring every soul to be subject to that which is the higher power and not the hat; and there is the humility where the soul is subject to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which is immortal, and the soul which is immortal; and so all worship set up in the transgression out of truth; and honour that is worldly and comes to dust, which men in the transgression cals civil, if they give them the hat it is a civil thing; it pacifies the rage of the transgressor, give him his Idol the hat, set up by the transgressors; but break down his Idol, and bring him to the witnesse in him to seek the honour which comes from above, from God, and turn him from the honor that is below, which God wil stain and lay in the Dust; and not give him this, the hat honour, hat worship, hat humility, and he will rage.</p>
            <p>But now before this honour which is from above, is the humility; and so that which is civil and leads into the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility destroys that which the transgressor sets up, and that which he would have, which is not civil, for that keeps but up the peace of the wicked, which must be broken, which stands in the feigned humility which is below; but the hat honor, the hat worship which hath his honor below, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30444:7"/>the feigned humility gets their honour from below, and the true humility is before the honour that is from above that turns from transgression; so all that would have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour they must not be furious nor passionate nor envious, for that is the fruit of the Heathen; they must have the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility before they have the true honour that is from above, which stains the other, and that which brings to the true humility; and that which brings men to the true humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, leads out of the transgression to the principle of God in them, and that all must come to, before they come to the Law of God which is equal, righteous and perfect, and goes over all transgressors, and lets them know the higher power which receives not honour of men; how can you believe that receives honour one of another, and not the honour that cometh of God onely? so there is the mark of the unbeliever: For how can you believe that receive honour one of another, and not the honour that comes from God onely; so they that receive honour one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are in the first <hi>Adam,</hi> which was in the transgression, and doth not receive the light which Christ Jesus hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened them withal, which will not receive honour from men, and the hat is an honour from below among men that are in the transgression, one of the transgressors Idols, which that must come to the dust which looks for it, and the hat both; and if they have not the hat civility, that nature will rage; so civility doth not come out of that ground, but it comes out of that ground which is out of the transgression.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> was a Judge and Judged in the Gates, and broke the Jawes of the wicked, he was legs to the lame, eyes to the blind, a help to the helplesse. <hi>Elihu</hi> saith to him who was a young man, <hi>I am full of the matter the spirit within me constrains me,</hi> And to the rest of his friends, <hi>Hear me, I pray you accept no mans person, neither let me give flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering titles to man; for I know not to give flattering titles; for in so doing my Maker would soon take me away.</hi> Now mark all ye that give flattering titles to men, and know how to give flattering titles to men, are not ye contrary to <hi>Elihu?</hi> did he speak a lie when he said his Maker would take him away
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30444:8"/>in so doing? And is not all these flattering titles? And peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath learned to know how to give flattering titles to men, and one to another; contrary to their Maker, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Elihu:</hi> and doth not the Maker take you away, sweep you away, who hath given up your selves to learn to know how to give flattering titles one to another? And is not this to please men? which if the Maker take them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for so doing, is not he against it? <hi>Job</hi> 32. Therefore beware all ye that are giving flattering titles to men, or a knowing how to give titles to men, least <hi>your Maker suddenly take you away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now such as fines people because they cannot swear, and will not take an Oath, but obeyes Christs command, who saith swearing was in the old time; and that they should perform their Oath to the Lord; but I say unto you now, Mark, now are you come to this, now, <hi>swear not at all, but let the communication be yea, yea, nay, nay, whatsoever is more cometh of evil; and above all things my brethren swear not at all,</hi> not by Heaven, not by Earth, not by any other Oath, lest you fall into condemnation; but in all your communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation let your yea be <hi>yea</hi> and your nay, <hi>nay;</hi> for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is more then these cometh of evil. Now you that compel, and fine and imprison the Brethren which keeps the commands of Christ, and cannot swear, and are the believers that cannot come into the condemnation among the swearers, are ye not all false Christians? have a name but are dead from the life, and such as have trampled upon Christs command and the Apostles; denies both their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and doth not his will? are you in him that hath all power in Heaven and Earth given unto him? Are you not all fallen into condemnation, according to the Apostles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? is not Christ the end of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Prophets, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and before they was that sware, and redeems men out of strife, in whom the Oath is the end of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie? Must not the Angel that swore bow to Christ who saith <hi>swear not at all,</hi> who hath all power in Heaven and earth given to him? Therefore all ye Magistrates upon the earth that hath fined the brethren, and imprisoned men because
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30444:8"/>they will not break the command of Christ, and transgress the Apostles Doctrine, and come into condemnation; But are at <hi>yea, and nay in their common occasions;</hi> and whatsoever is more then these is evil; and you are not onely trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressers of the Law of God and Christ, but are compellers of others to break the Law of Christ; and imprisons others and fines them if they will not; which they are ready if you will have any more then <hi>yea and na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> of the Saints and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to give the word of two or three witnesses, that so the word might be established; for Christ which was before Oaths, which was in the old time, and is the end of oaths, saith that <hi>in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word should be established;</hi> so saith the Apostle, who commands the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>above all things swear not at all;</hi> and tells them the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, least they fall into condemnation; but in all their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions keep to <hi>yea and nay,</hi> for whatsoever is more then these comes of evil; and men should be judged according to the Gospel when the secrets of all hearts should be revealed, and God will judge the World by the Man Christ Jesus, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s prepared and ordained, who is come to Judge the World in the righteousnesse, God will Judge them in equity according to the Law; for that is equity; who hath commanded yea and nay in their common occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Now you that make Acts for prophaning the Sabbath day, to make a fire, to gather sticks, to gath, meat on that day was a prophaning that day, for there was one stoned to death, and this was the <hi>Jews</hi> Sabbath, called the seventh day. Now the Saints meet together on the first day of the week, Christ rising on the first day, the first day of the week the Christians did not call the Sabbath; and so by your acts you corrupt Justice, stops the true Christians and the people of God from meeting together on the first day; and so contrary to the Act which saith they should not be hindred from meeting together to and fro to the worship and service of God, and they strain their goods, and take away Horses from them, and make havock of their goods, and spoiling, and carrying into prison contrary to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30444:9"/>their own Law, and the practise of the Apostles, as though they neither regarded the Law of God nor man, and the <hi>Instrument of Government</hi> saith, <hi>All that professe faith in Christ Jesus and own God, except they be Papist and Prelacy, except it be for licentiousnesse, though they differ in judgement, they shall be protected.</hi> Now the corrupt Justices acts contrary to this Instrument of Government, and throws it aside, and acts according to their own wills, and fines, and compells peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to come the Steeple-house; and so in many places in this Nation are worse then the <hi>Jews</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which did not so compel them, the Christians after conversion, to come to their Temple, or Synagogue, or Offering, this is contrary to the Law of equity and Gospel, compelling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to do that which they would not do themselves; for would they be compelled to come to all other Christians meetings? and this is to bring people into Wildernesses and to quench the spirit; Now the Law is to keep down mens wils; and that men should not act in their own wills: if they do usurp, and act Illegally, and unequally, and so become Tyrants, which the Lord rebukes for his elect sake, and Judges, and cuts off: Now there is an act made <hi>that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny shall speak to a Priest that is called a Minister while he is going to the Steeple-house, or from it, maliciously or on set purpose, he shall be fined or sent to the house of correction, or six Moneths impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned;</hi> Now malicious wickednesse is to be stoped and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by this act corrupt Justices in their wils makes such use of and destroys the liberty and order; comforting and edification of the Church; for if any thing be revealed to another that sits by let the first hold his peace, <hi>for you may all prophesie one by one, that all may learn and be comforted,</hi> so that if any speak as he is moved of the Lord God, or reprove a Priest for his pride, and lets him see when he errs in his Doctrine, going or coming from the Steeple-house, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people, he is sent away to Prison, as a malicious disturber by the Justices and Priest, who hath got a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of swearers to swear the other did it maliciously or wickedly, and so are become Judges of their hearts, and so seeks to destroy the Authority of the Church which all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30444:9"/>may speak one by one. Ah poor people that you should have no more insight into things, for this is for stopping the word of God, and limiting the spirit, and against the Apostles Doctrine, and against the Church of Christ, and so holding up Antichrists Church, and persecution, that men should have no more patience, but persecute the people of God, that fears God, and speaks his words; now, and if they were gain-sayers to convince them, that they should have no more Authority that calls themselves Ministers, but for goals and houses of correction, who are <hi>Cains,</hi> and kills <hi>Abel,</hi> who have the marks of the false Prophets; who wears the Sheeps cloathing, the beast and Antichrist, slaies and kills the Saints and brethren, who hath the spiritual weapons to wrestle with the powers of darknesse, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wrastles with flesh and blood, and casts that into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: And like unto the <hi>Jews</hi> that turned against Christ, and the Apostles of Christ, and the Saints; for the sheep the Lambs, never killed, the Goats, and the Wolves, and worried them, but they got the Sheeps cloathing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might deceive and worry, tear and destroy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might be like the Sheep, having the outside; so now, they are discovered from the Sheep by their fruits; &amp; so by Justices have people bin compelled to go to steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses, and prisoned for not going, and prisoned for going, when they are moved of the Lord, and so men by this act have made a prey upon the innocent and the just, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hath been prisoned, and whipt, and beat for speaking the word of the Lord God, as they are moved of the Lord, freely as they have received, and not for stipends, and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, and gleab lands. Then there is an act for <hi>vagabonds, and sturdy beggers,</hi> and this the Justices have turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the righteous, for when the Sons of God, and his servants, and daughters, have been moved to reprove sin in the gates; drunkards or swearers, or to speak the word of the Lord in the markets, and reprove them for their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zening and cheating, and exhorted them to yea and nay in their common occasions, they have taken them up and whipt them for Rogues and sturdy beggers, the servants
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30444:10"/>and sons and daughters of the Lord God; and thus the sword is turned backward upon the righteous, and he that reproves sin in the gate is become a prey. Now this Act would have often took hold upon the Prophets who went into the Temple, and cryed to the heads and Rulers, and declared against their sins and transgressions, therefore take heed of making any thing as to hold up sin and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, or turning that upon them that is made for sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and transgressors upon the righteous which are sent of the Lord to cry against sin and sinners, and to reprove them, and this act, by the malitious, would often have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold on Christ &amp; his Apostles, who often went among the Jewes, to cry against their Synagogues, and Temple. Now if you say, it takes hold upon none, but upon the malitious and the wicked, then let none that are wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed execute it, nor the malitious, for the malitious will turn against the righteous, and such quencheth the spirit of God in themselves and stops it in others, and will follow and hold up that which God never commanded, and such Prophets and shepherds, which are of the earth, and the worlds teaching for money and the fleece, seeking for their gain from their quarter, such run, but God never sent them.</p>
            <p>And the last Parliament made an act, that such <hi>as denyed the Sacraments and the Scriptures to be the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scriptures of truth are the words of God, as in the twentieth chapter of <hi>Exodus, God spake all these words,</hi> and Christ saith, my words, and <hi>John</hi> saith in the <hi>Revelation, he that adds to these words,</hi> and takes from these, (Mark) words not a word, and <hi>Christ is the word</hi> saith <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Revelations,</hi> who comes to fulfill the words of God, which was before the words was in whom the words ends.</p>
            <p>And the words, Sacraments, there is no Scripture will hold them up but the Papists common prayer book, and that act will take hold upon the Apostles.</p>
            <p>A Priest sends for a Writ from <hi>London</hi> out of the Courts that such a man must appear in his own person, and when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30444:10"/>he appeares in his own person, they will not take it for an appearance, but he must appear by an Attorney; now this is contrary to the Law, which is, <hi>so speak and so do.</hi> And the Priests will sue men and women in the Courts at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and make them go, it may be, two hundred miles: the Priest doth not preach to them, they do no work for them, they have not hired them; and thus they will sue them for a matter of a groat or twelve pence, &amp;c. as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, whom they do no work for; and this is not equal nor righteous, nor according to the Law nor Gospel, which is equity; and that is not a Court of Equity that will give the Priest that: And the Priests put in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations against them they have sued, whom they do no work for; and they will say in their Declarations, that he hath thirty loads of Corn, so many Pigs and Geese, so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loads of Wheat, and so many Kine, and this he puts in at the Courts at <hi>London;</hi> a multitude of lyes, when as he hath not a quarter so many, and some not at all, not a Pig, nor a Goose, nor a cock of Barly; and them that have such things, they will put in their Bill and Declaration three times as much as they have, and so this large Bill three times more then a man hath, the Priest puts against him he doth no work for; the poor man in taking a Copy of it, must give eight pence <hi>per</hi> sheet, and it may be the sheet doth not consist of above sixteen lines; and then when the poor man hath proved the Priests Bill to be full of lies, the lyer is not punished, that works not for the poor man; <hi>I will have meanes,</hi> saith he that is called the Priest; and then the poor man gives in his answer against his lyes, that hath done no work for, nor hired him; and then the Judges they will not take it, unless the poor man will swear and break Christs command, and deny himself to be a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and enter into the Jews and Heathens state, and become like them, swearers, which Christ and the Apostles saith, <hi>swear not at all;</hi> then cryes the rash, and fierce, and furious Judge, will be not swear? take him away, and cast him into prison, into the <hi>Fleet,</hi> and there lyes eight of them, besides more in many Goales of the Nation because they cannot
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30444:11"/>swear; and then when the Judge and Priest hath gotten this Christian into prison, because he will not swear to his answer, then the Priest goes home, and makes havock of this poor mans goods, and takes his very corn, beasts, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, plough-gear, and beds, cheese, bed-clothes, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens clothes, shifts, to the very childrens bibs; and thus many Christians, because they will not break Christs command, and give him meanes, them they do not work for, are thus used by them whom they never hired; but their rejoycing is in the Lord, and comfort, and not in men that will not do them justice; the cry is now, <hi>if he will not swear take him away,</hi> and if he will not give the Priest tythes, though he never hired the Priest, nor set him on work, take treble damage of him, and then wreck him; and then the Priests who hath a Commission, whose consciences are so seared, to take of them they no work for; they will take treble and treble, as you may read in the book called, <hi>The sufferings about Tythes.</hi> Now if these doings is not the way to bring the hand of the Lord up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Nation, judge ye that are wise and sober in heart, and what Courts these are, that have no more feeling of justice amongst them, to plead the cause of the poor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men, that are not skill'd in their wayes and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Now saith the Writ the Priest hath brought forth, <hi>you must appear in your own persons;</hi> when the poor man comes two hundred miles to the Court, and doth appear by the Writ, though the Priest hath done no work for him, nor he hath not hired him, saith the Court, <hi>you must appear by an Attorney,</hi> this sayes the Court; but sayes the poor man, did not you grant out a Writ that I should appear in my own person? I but sayes the Court, you must fee an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, give him ten groats; I but sayes the poor man, why did you wrong me by a Writ, and bring me up hither, and say I must appear in my own person; and how can I say I appeared in my own person, or how can you say I appeared in my own person, when the Attorney appeares for me? and so I make you lyers, and my self both in this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30444:11"/>case; and so I see the seat of justice is not amongst you: then the poor man cryes, and is grieved to see the Bar stand up against Justice and Innocency, and sayes the poor man, I am able to plead my own cause, and the Judges of old was to hear the cause of the poor as well as the rich, and there is no talk of Attorneys, or ten groats fees to them, and I am able to plead my own cause: Oh how are the Judges lost from the state they were at first in the dayes of <hi>Moses,</hi> cryes the poor man, that I cannot be heard except I will give an Attorney money, and give him a gift? oh sayes the poor man, this is contrary to <hi>Moses,</hi> this is contrary to the Judges of old, and the Prophets of God, who said, Gifts blind the eyes of the wise; oh sayes the poor man, now I see the wise eyes are blinded with their gifts, <hi>Lord help me, for thou art just, who judgeth amongst the Judges,</hi> how contrary are these to thy servant <hi>Moses;</hi> who bids the Judges hear the cause of the poor as well as the rich, and now I cannot be heard neither in answer nor in appearance, except I will fee an Attorney, give him ten groats, ten shillings to a Counsellor, though I know my cause my self, and am able to speak of it: Justice was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bought nor sold for money, for that is of God free, saith the poor man.</p>
            <p>When I have entred in my appearance, and taken a copy of the Declaration against me, and given in my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, the Judge and Court will not receive it, unlesse I will transgresse my Redeemers command, and swear; oh grief! oh lamentable cryes the poor man, the cause of all these things coming out against me is the Priest, he hath done no work for me, I have not hired him, yet he sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons me up two hundred miles, I must appear personal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and when I come there, the Judge tels me, that gave forth the Writ, I must appear by an Attorney, and fee him, cryes the poor man, here is no truth neither in Priests, nor Judges, nor Courts, who say I must appear personally, and when I come here, an Attorney must appear for me, and make me a lyer: Oh lamentable, cryes the poor man, is justice fallen to the ground? who would have thought
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30444:12"/>the Judges had been so; and when I give in my answer, I must have a Counsellors hand, and he must have ten shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: Ah saith the poor man, <hi>you are for money, I am for justice,</hi> I know my own cause, I need not have a Counsellor: The Law being grounded upon Reason, I know Reason and unreasonablenesse, so I by that meanes, and every poor man, is able to plead his own cause, and appear in his own person without Attorney and Counsellor: And sayes the poor man to the Judge and Lawyers, how can you give these men, according to Reason, on which the Law is grounded, treble damage of me, whom he hath done no work for, nor I never hired him, neither is he my Teacher, Christ is my Teacher, neither is he my Priest, Christ is my Priest, neither is he my Leader, Christ is my Leader, neither is he my Bishop, Christ is my Bishop: Alack for you, sayes the poor man, I look'd for justice amongst you, and equity, and the Law of God amongst you, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Scripture, to doe as you would be done by, should another man come and take treble damage of you that never did work for you, you never hired, nor you owe him nothing? now consider this, that the Law is, <hi>to do as you would be done by,</hi> and the Lord is my help, saith the poor man.</p>
            <p>Now it is an unjust thing for one man to be compelled by a Law to mend another mans house, anothers meeting-house, which they worship in, as to mend the old Mass-house, called the Church, in which the world sets up their worship, for all these Masse-houses was set up since the dayes of the Apostles, set up East and West with a cross at the end of them: Now them that will have them, let them maintain them, if they will, if they will not, they shew but their covetousnesse, and a dishonour to their Church; and them that will have a Ministery let them maintain it, and keep them within the Law and Gospel, and let them not sue other Congregations and Assemblies to maintain them they do no work for, for that is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and unrighteous; so every Congregation and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly maintain their own Ministers, if they will have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30444:12"/>them, that they like best, and let none be cast into prison about Religion, and let not a Minister or another Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation goe out of his own to sue another of anothers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and cast him into prison till death if he will not give it him: The Lord God is come to teach his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple himself, and these shall not be the Teachers of his people, that will destroy mens lives for meanes, neither do they follow Christ, who comes to save mens lives; so that is a false Ministry, who will destroy mens lives for meanes; let every one maintain his own meeting-place; and his own Minister, that will have one, and there is the Law of Equity, for should all the Congregations, the <hi>Quakers. Baptists, Independents, Seekers Brownists</hi> compel the Priests to maintain their meeting-place, or give their Speakers maintenance, and if the Priest would not give it them, sue them at the Law, have them before Courts; cast them into prison till death, get a company of men and spoil their goods, take away their cheese, bedding, shifts, clothes, swine, wooll, corn, beasts, horses, plough-geer, the very bibs for children, and drink their beer, and let the rest which they cannot drink flow on the floor, as the Priest did in <hi>Kent</hi> and his company? or again, should the <hi>Independents</hi> compel the <hi>Baptists,</hi> or the <hi>Baptists</hi> the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> to maintain their meeting-house and Minister, if not, cast them into prison, and hale them before Courts? or should the <hi>Quakers</hi> compel the <hi>Independents,</hi> or <hi>Baptists,</hi> or <hi>Seekers,</hi> or the Priests, to maintain their meeting-house and their Speaker, and cast them into prison till death if they would not, and spoil their goods, such as they doe no work for, as the Priests doe, then they should be their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and follow them; but they abhorre such things, who have Christ and the Apostles for their examples, and they follow them.</p>
            <p>And for an Indictment to be drawn against a man, <hi>That he went over a mans ground with carts, and horses, and sheep, and oxe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> when he went over but only a hedge, on foot himself: Is this simplicity or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uity, <hi>so say and so do,</hi> which is the Law? Must not the Lyer be punished here according to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30444:13"/>the Law of God? <hi>but this is our forme</hi> said the Judges; but is this the form of sound words which the Apostle bids keep to? have you not trampled upon his doctrine and slighted it? and got into a form of unsound words, and denied the form of sound words? An Indictment is drawn against a man, and in the Indictment it is said, that <hi>the man struck him with a fork, sword, staffe, and with bis;</hi> it may be he never lift up his hand against him; <hi>this is our forme</hi> say they: Now this is not a form of sound words, <hi>so say and so de,</hi> but a form of unsound words, and so judged by the Law of Liberty; <hi>and so though we send out Writs, that every man shall appear in his own person, and when he comes before us we tell him, he should appear by an Attorney, and give him ten groats, and ten shillings to a Counsellor, how should we Lawyers live else? we may hang our tools on the hedge,</hi> say they: I but sayes the poor man, I know Equity and reason, to give thee ten shillings to set thy hand to this, and ten groats to an Attorney, and eight pence a sheet, when it may be there is not above sixteen lines in the sheet, this is unreasonable; and whereas you say, I must appear in my own person, and now you tell me, I must appear by an Attorney, <hi>this is our form</hi> sayes the Judge. I but sayes the poor man, this is not a form of sound words, nor the form of the Law of God, so say and so do, but this is the form of lyes; for if I say I will appear in my own person, and you say I must appear in my own person such a day, and if I doe not appear I should be a lyer, and if I doe appear, and you will not take it, then you are lyers; so you are not come to the form of sound words: and saith the poor man, I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven eight pence a sheet which hath not above sixteen lines in it: The Priest hath put in against me, and he saith, I have thirty load of corn, and so many sheep, and beasts, and oxen, when I have not half so many: and saith another poor man, prisoned at <hi>Hartford,</hi> the Priest declares, I had so many ducks, geese, calves, and cowes, and apples, when I had none, this is our form, saith the Judge of the Court; oh dear! saith the poor man, what a form of lyes? this is not a form of sound words; oh
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30444:13"/>have you trampled down the Apostles Doctrine, and true christians, who should keep the form of sound words! but that is the form of lyes, for I keep never a pig, nor duck, nor hen, nor goose, nor calfe; and did not <hi>Moses</hi> and the chief Magistrates and Judges at the first say, lyers should be punished, and that which he thought to doe to another should be done to him? And how can ye have such a form? who is the Author of this form amongst you? An Indictment that a man went over a ground with carts and horses, when he went over a hedge on foot; that a man struck a man with swords, and bils, and pikes, when he hardly lift up his hand against him; that a man hath thirty load of corn, and a hundred of sheep, and thirty geese, and so many cherries and plums, when he hath not a quarter so many; a man must appear in his own person, and then they will not take it without an Attorney; is not this a lye found in this Writ, and a lye in all your formes? unsound words, not a form of sound words that cannot be condemned, but a form or unsound words, which is to be condemned, which is not a forme of truth.</p>
            <p>Would it not have been an unrighteous thing in the dayes of the Apostles, for the Jews and Gentiles convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to be compelled to maintain the Jewes Priests, and mend their Temples, and the Gentiles to have maintained the Jewes and their Priests which was not converted, as now people are compelled since the dayes of the Apostles, in the Apostacy, to maintain the Popes Masse-house, and the Priests made at his Schooles by the will of men, and preaches at his houses, as <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge, <hi>Emanuel,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> St. <hi>Peter.</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi> St. <hi>Austins?</hi> here is the Popes names that he names his houses by.</p>
            <p>And it is unequal and unjust for prisoners to be brought into a court by a Goaler, and the Judge and court say, he came in by force of armes, because he would not pull off his hat as the Judge said at <hi>Lanceston.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is an unequal thing for a man coming into a court before a Judge, and because he will not put off his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30444:14"/>hat, fine him forty pounds, or a hundred Mark to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, and the prisoner that is fined by him, asketh him for a Law, instruct me in that Law, or that custom, if it be a custome, who was the Author of it, or where is it written in Baliwick or Wappentake? who was the first Author of them? in what Statute is this Law written, that I must pull off my hat, and uncover my head, which is for the service of it? for the Law is for the uncovering of people of all corruption and unrighteousnesse, and for the keeping down mens wils, who would usurp Authority, and for keeping of men from respecting of persons, for such as doe, are convinced by the Law to be transgressors; and so say and so doe, and he that so sayes and doth not, is judged by the Law of Liberty, and the Law is that all men should doe equally and righteously, and that is the higher power called, and that goes over all unrighteous power evil doers, and sinners, and there is a terror to them, and murtherers, and is life for life, and bloud for bloud; and if a thief steal restore five fold, or four fold, or to be sold for his theft, and if they kill a thief in the day time, there shall be bloud shed for him.</p>
            <p>And when the Judge is askt by the prisoner concerning the hat, what Law and custom is for it, and where he may read it? Oh cryes the Judge, and swels, and rages, and full of fury, I doe not carry my Law books upon my back; I but saith the poor prisoner, the Judges of old was legs to the lame, and eyes to the blind, and a help to the helpless, and why wilt not thou and you inform me of that Law and custome that sayes, I must be fined a hundred mark, and forty pounds, if I will not put off my hat to you: why will not you instruct me in that Law? why will you keep me and poor people blind, and not instruct me in that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, if it be one? saies the Judge, if you will put off your hat I will do you justice, if not take him away Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; and thus the poor prisoner goes away uninformed in the Law and custom, not knowing the ground and author of it, the Judge not informing him, contrary to <hi>Moses</hi> and the Judges of old, and the Scripture, which saith, They
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30444:14"/>shall teach them in the Law, and instruct them in the Law, yea and teach their children the Law, that all might know it and fear.</p>
            <p>Now putting off the hat is but a custome got up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Christians (and fining for not doing it) since the Apostles in the Apostacie, a vain custome, set up by Traditions, which is a worship of men, and of the beast, and honour below, and an Idol set up by transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors; and saies the poor prisoner, I never read in all the Courts among all the heathen upon the earth, from the foundations of the world, among all the Courts, and Kings, and Judges, and Magistrates, amongst the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, that ever they required, or had any Law or custome, that men should put off their hats that came before them, or else be fined a hundred marks, or forty pounds, or more, or lesse, to the chief Magistrate of the Nation, lie in prison, or pay it; and I never read amongst all the Assemblies or Congregations of the Saints, that was amongst the Apostles before the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacie, that ever Christ the King, the chief Bishop, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, Shepherd, Law-giver, who hath the Government upon his shoulders, that he or his Apostles commanded any to put off their hars that came before them, if not fine them a hundred marks, or forty pounds, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prison them till payment. Now there is a custome, that is vain, Heathens set up that be in the transgression, which is an Idol, an honour below, which is the hat, which men if they have it not, they are all in a rage, and will not doe them justice without it; so the hat makes all men in transgression fooles, and destroyes their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, their worship, not giving it, and throws down their Idol, and such seek the honour which is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and worships God in the spirit, and comes into the good custom: You deny civility, cry they, in not bowing the hat to us; that which rageth, which hath not the hat bowed to it, is not in the civility. Now civility is that that destroyes rage, and brings men out of transgression, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30444:15"/>destroyes the Idols honour below, and will-worship, and brings men out of transgression, in which there stands peace &amp; no rage, and this is civilitie, and curtesie, known out of transgression, will-worship, and honour below.</p>
            <p>The prisoners are brought into the court, the Gaoler, or the cryer knocks off their hats, takes them from them, the Judge is angry and wrath, give them their hats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, saith the Judge, and the poor simple prisoners puts them on; put off your hat, saith the Judge to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner again; shew me a Law saith the poor prisoner; I will shew you none, saith the Judge, I doe not carry my Law books on my back; shew me where it is written; take them away Gaoler, I will ferk them, saith the Judge <hi>Glynn,</hi> they will destroy both the Magistrates, &amp; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Ministrie: Ah cries the poor prisoner, doth the hat destroy Magistrates, and Government, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrie both? doth it all end in the hat; and will a hat destroy Ministers and Magistrates? I own Magistrates, and the higher Power, (doe me justice) and I own the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of Christ, made by the will of God, that will not destroy mens lives for tithes, and spoil their goods, and destroy their families, making havock of their goods that they doe no work for, but such as teach for filthy lucre, love of money, bear rule by their meanes, seek for their gain from their quarter, can never have enough, seek for the fleece, divine for money, called of men Master, which Christ saith, be not ye so, ye are all brethren; you have one Master, even Christ, and therefore such as Christ and the Apostles cried against, and disallowed; I dare not own, I fear God, who disapproves such, and ownes his Prophets, and his Son, and his Apostles, and heares him; so such as God sends I own, (not of men) so I own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates and Ministers, and honour the higher Power with my soul; the Prophets and Apostles of old, and Christ declared against the false Prophets, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, and Ministers, and the corruptions that was in them, therefore doth that follow, that they deny the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30444:15"/>true Magistrates and Ministers? and what a Ministrie and Magistracie is that, which will be destroyed with the hat? Oh what a covering of darknesse is got over you! and of prejudice and hardnesse of heart and wickednesse, that now in the ancient of dayes a hat makes such work with you? how doth your transgression appear out of the life of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Judge of all <hi>Israel,</hi> the Kings said, uncover not your heads; and <hi>David</hi> the King, <hi>Samuel</hi> 2 15. and <hi>Moses</hi> the Judge, <hi>Leviticus</hi> 10. and <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> in all his fury and rage, did not cast the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into the fiery furnace because they would not bow the hat to him, or his courts, or Judges, or Officers, he did not bid fine them, cast them into prison; it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read throughout all the world, that ever any had a Law or a custome to fine men a hundred marks, or forty pounds, because they would not bow the hat to them, or cast them into prison till payment; and more hath been cast into prison, and fined by the Judges and courts within this age, then ever was in any in the world before, or ever was read of by you which call yourselves the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, churches, Ministers, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and nothing will appease your wrath, but that which comes from the dust, and turnes to dust; must not that honour be laid in the dust, that looks for that that comes from the dust, and returnes to the dust? and is not that the transgressor, that seeks not for the honour which comes from God; when will ye be wise ye Judges and Rulers of the earth, and be instructed, and learn the humility that goes before the honour, that you might be honoured in the hearts of all the people? and to live in the higher power, which every ones soul must be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, and that honours it; it is an honour for a man to cease from strife, and to be humble, and to do justice without respect of persons, or without respect of a hat; for if a Lord or an Earl come into your courts, you will hardly fine him for not putting off his hat, for coming before you, but it is the poor that suffers, and the rich
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30444:16"/>bears with the rich, and the poor have been trodden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot, and the Servants of the Lord for a thing of naught.</p>
            <p>And the Scripture saith, <hi>Thou shalt not let sin lie upon thy brother, but reprove them,</hi> and thus saith the Law of God and <hi>Moses</hi> the chief Magistrate; but when this Law was transgressed, they that reproved sin in the gates was made a prey upon, and made himself a prey; and now you persecute them as sturdy Beggars, which beg not at all of you, and such you whip and prison as vagrants, and let vagrants go free, and sturdy beggers up and down your Towns, which is a dishonour to your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Church, Ministry, Teaching, Government, and worse then the Jewes, who had tithes, which tithes was enough for <hi>Levi,</hi> widdows, strangers, and fatherlesse, and that there need not be a begger amongst them; and such as reprove sin in your gates, Markets and Steeple-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and be in the life of the Apostles and Prophets, you persecute them, and whip them, and imprison them, and send them away with Passes, as vagabonds and sturdie beggers, as witnesse <hi>Marlborough,</hi> and many parts in the West. Now a vagabond is one that is in the wrath and envie, and a murtherer, that hath not a habitation in God, that hath not eternal life abiding in him, and all sturdie beggers; and sturdinesse is come in by trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression amongst the wasters, oppressors, and destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the fall, from the Image of God and transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of it, which the Law provides, added because of transgression, the higher power, that there shall not be a begger, and the commandement given, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law, which takes the tenths, will give e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to strangers, fatherlesse, widdows, <hi>Levi</hi> the Priest. Now that Priest that takes tithe, the tenths, and will not give the fatherlesse, widdows, and stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers enough, that there be not a begger amongst them, he is not under the Law. Now the Gospel, the power of God to salvation to every one that believes; where
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30444:16"/>where Christ is known the Redeemer from the earth, the ninths and tenths both, to reign upon it, there is no begger there, he reignes upon the earth; this was amongst the Apostles; now they that have set up ninths and tenths since the dayes of the Apostles, they are Apostates, and their tenths they do not make use of to fill the widdows, to fill the strangers, to fill the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlesse, so tramples under the Ordinance of God, (according as they doe professe) tenths or tithes, and yet they will say, they are Ministers of Christ, and the Gospel; they are unlike to them (or the Law) which saith, the Priesthood was changed that took tithes, and the Commadment disanulled that gave them, and the Ordinance blotted out, and so they preach Christ and the Gospel, which redeems people out of the ninths and tenths, up to God, to reign upon it; and thus you have lost your savour, and acts contrary to Scripture, and are become that salt that Christ speaks of.</p>
            <p>Let all Judges, Lawyers, Attorneys and Clerkes, lay down their fees, and gifts, and all Priests or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters lay down their tithes, stipends, gleab-lands, <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> reckonings, Midsummer dues, offerings, the Popes wages, let them all go out free, Judges, Priests, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, Lawyers, Attorneys, and none to judge for money, nor preach for money, tithes, nor land, nor of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and then it will be seen who loves his neighbour as himself, who will come to the Law from that which blinds him, and then it shall be seen who will preach the Gospel freely, that they may live of it, and who will thresh, and plant vineyards, and get flocks, and this will be the way to restore Judges, as they were at first, out of that which blinded them, and to restore Ministers as they were in the dayes of the Apostles, into that they were in, and this is the Word of the Lord God to you all; and then you shall see who will be serviceable to the Creation, and glorifie God in his Generation, and to judge for God without respect, such will
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30444:17"/>break the jawes of the wicked, and are eyes to the blind, and legs to the lame, and a help to them that cannot help themselves, and here the higher powers shall be known, which high and low, rich and poor, all must come to the light, that of God in them, which Christ hath enlightned them withall, before they see it, feel it, and receive it.</p>
            <p>And it is an unequal thing for people to pay Clerks wages for saying <hi>Amen,</hi> when the people are such as do not hear him that he demands wages of; if they will not give it him, he will strein their goods, and make havock of them; and this never was in all ages known amongst the Jews, or Heathen, or Apostles, but amongst the Apostates since the Apostles, that ever any had wages and money to say <hi>Amen</hi> and other things, as giving the <hi>Psalm,</hi> and turning the hour-glasse, which the Priest prayes and preaches by: Now this Clerk will have money of them that doth not hear the Priest, nor hear him say <hi>Amen,</hi> that are of other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations his own Congregation is not able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him; now it is known, proved, and tried, that the Priest will not pray without money, but he will have money for it, and preach without money, and sing without money <hi>Davids</hi> prayers, prophesyings, quakings, fastings, reproachings, cryings, wastings, &amp;c. without money, and by the glasse sell it out, by the glasse that is his measure, and will have money of them that will not buy of him, nor have none of their merchandize, and heares them not, and sets them not at work; and yet these that sells and preaches Christ, and the Apostles, and Prophets words for money, by the hour-glasse, that is the Priests measure, some two or three measures of a day, (there was one moved of the Lord to goe into the Steeple-house, and take down the Priests glasse before his face, which he was persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for, and like to have lost his life, which was at <hi>Kendal</hi>) and so such the Lord accepts, that sings free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30444:17"/>and prayes freely, in the spirit to the Lord, who knows the mind of it, and such comes to know the Scriptures, which was given forth from the Spirit of God; and such as are Ministers of the Spirit, the Lord accepts, and sings in the Spirit, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships God in the Spirit, they come to live in that that gave forth Scriptures; and doe not make a Trade of the Scriptures, words given forth in ages past.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some passages and proceedings in Courts.</head>
               <p>WHen a Writ of <hi>Sub poena</hi> goes out of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer or Chancerie, it commands a man to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in his own person such a day, on pain of a hundred pound; &amp; when the poor man comes to the Court honestly, as the Writ commands, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Law, there stands men, called tip-staves, with great staves in their hands, and cries, be uncovered, you, put off your hat, or else it is a contempt; Saies the poor man, this Writ commands me to appear this day in my own person, on pain of a hundred pound; then the tip-staves puls him and hales him, and saies, he shall not come in, and keeps him out, and bids go get an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney to appear for him; then the poor man waits till the Judges rise, and when they come forth of the court tels them, that he is come to appear in his own person, as the Writ commands him: the Judges bids him goe to the Office and get an Attorney; the poor man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, this Writ of mine commands me, all excuses set
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30444:18"/>apart, to appear in my own person, and here I am, is not this appearance? No, said <hi>Roger Hill,</hi> one of the Barons of the Exchequer, this is not appearance; (take notice Reader) the Statute Law saith, a man shall appear in his own proper person, and the common Law saith, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance is the parties coming into the court: And whether shall the poor man believe, the Law, or Baron <hi>Hill? Body of the Common Law,</hi> ch. 42 by <hi>E. W.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the poor man goes to the Office, and tels an Attorney that he hath appeared, and desires him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord his appearance which he hath made, and he will give him four-pence for his recording it (which is his due;) saies the Attorney, you must first give me ten groats to appear for you, and then I will record it for four pence; the poor man replies, I have appeared my self in my own person, as the Law commanded me, and therefore it is a very unreasonable thing to ask me ten groats for work that I have done my self; saies the Attorney, that is not appearance, you must fee an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, for you cannot appear your self; then saies the poor man, this is a false Writ, take it again, and make it right the next time, and command an Attorney to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and discharge me: No, no, saies the Attorney, the Writ is true, and it is yours, but you must get an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney to appear for you; saies the poor man, my Writ does not say so, for there is not such a word as Attorney in it, but it commands me expresly to appear in my own person; well, well, saies the Attorney, give me ten groats and I will appear for you, and then I am your person; that cannot be, saies the poor man, ten groats can never change my person, and therefore I desire thee record my own appearance which I have made, and that will be truth without any lying or dissembling, and I will pay thee for thy paines; saies the Attorney, but if I should record your appearance in your own person, what will become of me and all other Attorneys here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after? Saies another Attorney, if such as you come we
<pb facs="tcp:30444:18"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:30444:19"/>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:30444:19"/>may goe hang our tools on the hedge; the poor man replies, I have nothing to doe with what you doe with your tooles, if you had not sent this Writ for me, which commands me to appear in my own person, I could have been very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to stay at home and follow my work, but seeing the Law commanded me, I thought it my duty to come and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Law, for the Apostle saies, Let every soul be subject to the higher powers; indeed if I had been fick, or lame, or impotent in my body, that I had not been able to come, then I had a very good excuse, and the Law hath made a very good provision in such a case, in a Statute made the seventh year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, chap. 13. the words of the Statute are these as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item.</hi> Whereas many of the Kings liege people be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed, and many waved by erronious processe, and be so impotent in their bodies by divers malidies &amp; infirmities, that they may not come in their proper persons before the King in his Bench, there to make their suit; to reverse such erronious processe, It is ordained, and established, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Justice, of the one Bench, and of the other, and also the chief Baron of the Exchequer shall have power to examine the same persons, having such malady and diseases openly known; and thereupon may the same Justices, and the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and every of them, by their discretion, record their Attorney in this case, provided alwaies, that in the Writ of <hi>Capias ad satisfaciendum</hi> the common Law shall hold place.</p>
               <p>And also by another Statute, made in the seventh year of King <hi>Richard</hi> the second, it was agreed, That if any man which is of good same be out of the Realm, in such a case he may have an Attorney, and such Attorneys, in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of their Masters, may answer for them, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But (saies the poor man) though these be very good Laws, yet this is not my case, for I am not beyond sea, nor sick, nor lame, nor impotent, and therefore I am bound by the Law to appear in my own person.</p>
               <p>(Saies an Attorney) thou are an impudent fellow, to come to take away our Trade: saies another Attorney if you will not have an Attorney to appear for you, we will
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30444:20"/>send an Attachment for you, and commit you to prison for a contempt.</p>
               <p>Take notice all honest men, if the poor man appear in proper person, as the Law commands him, and will not fee an Attorney, as their will only commands him, this the Lawyers cals a contempt; and judge honestlie now between the poor man and the Lawyers, whether this be a contempt or not. Then if the poor man, for fear of the pretended contempt, doe fee an Attorney, then saies the Attorney, you must answer the bill, or else you will be in contempt; saies the poor man, give me the hill, and then I will answer it; but saies the Attorney, you must first give a rule; a rule, what is that? (saies the poor man) give me a groat (saies the Attorney) and I will give a rule for you, for you cannot doe it your self; then the poor man gives him a groat, and then he writes or speaks a few words to the Plaintiffs Attorney to bring in the bill: now saies the Attorney, you must an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer this bill, or else you will be in contempt; give me it then (saies the poor man) and I will give him an answer to it; no, no, (saies the Attorney) I must take a copy of it for you, and you must give me eight-pence a sheet for it; that is very dear (saies the poor man) &amp; I work very hard a great while for a little money, and truly I am not willing to part with it so lightly, but if you will write me a copy for as much money as I could get by my work while you are wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, I should be very willing to pay you, for I am very willing to do as I would be done by; but I will not do so (saies the Attorney) for I must have eight-pence a sheet for it; then (saies the poor man) if you will not write it for a reasonable price, let me see it, and I can write it my self, or else get my friend to write it for me; no, no, (saies the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney) we will not let you have the Record to write a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie of it your self, nor your friend neither, you must appoint an Attorney to write a copy of it for you; well then (saies the poor man) it appears that I have power to appoint an Attorney to write a copie of the bill for me, &amp; without me no Attorney can, nor dare meddle with it, and therefore either write it for me at my price, or else give me it, and I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30444:20"/>will write it my self; what a strange man are you (saies the Attorney) do you think that we must work at the same rate as you work at? why should you not (saies the poor man) for the Scripture saith, <hi>Whatsoever you would that men should do unto you, do you so unto them;</hi> well, well, (saies the Attorney) but my fees are due unto me by the Law of the Land; it is true indeed (saies the poor man) there was a Statute made in the seventh year of King <hi>Richard</hi> the second, &amp; the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth chapter, which saith, that Attorneys in the absence of their Master may answer for them, and therefore I being Master am willing to give thee as much as I can get my self, &amp; me thinks thou shouldst be content with it, for I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to work for two pence half penny an hour, that is half a crown a day, &amp; work but twelve hours on a day, &amp; I think that is good honest wages, &amp; if thou will not work as cheap as I do, I being thy master, let me do my work my self; but my parents bred me up to this (saies the Attorney, and it cost them a great deal of money, &amp; me a great deal of time, before I got any money for my self, and then how do you think my labour should be as cheap as yours? Well, (saies the poor man) my parents also bred me up, and gave money to bind me apprentice, and then I served seven or eight years before I got money for my self, then reckon my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and my time, as well as thy money and thy time, and then why should not my labour be as good as thine? And now I ask thee by what Law thou demandest eight-pence a sheet? It is the rules of the Court (saies the Attorney) and also an ancient custome; I have heard some say (saith the poor man) that it is a maxime in Law, that an evil custome is to be abolished, and truly I think it a very bad custome, that would compel me to pay an Attorney 8 d. a sheet, and have so few words in a sheet, that a Lawyer or his boy can write nine sheets of it in an hour, how can you in consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ask me five or six shillings an hour for every hours writing, and when thou hast done, I could write as much my self in one sheet as thou writes in twentie, besides I know this, that many times thou hast more work then thou canst do thy self, and then thou hires another man to write
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30444:21"/>for thee, and then thou gives him but a penny a sheet, and wouldst thou take 8 d. a sheet of me, for that which he can afford to do for a penny a sheet? this is contrarie to equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and good conscience; besides <hi>Magna charta</hi> saith, we will sell no man justice nor right; and therefore I am very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly used, if I can neither have justice nor right except I buy it at such a dear rate: Well, well, (saies the Attorney) if you will not take a copy of the bill and put in an answer, it will be a contempt; then if the poor man take a copie of the bill at this unreasonable rate for fear of a contempt, in reading it over he sinds many things in it that are not true, &amp; then he tels the Lawyer that there is many things in this bill that is not true, and asks why they put such things in? this is our formalitie (saies the Attorney;) then your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malitie lies (saies the poor man:) And then if the poor man write a plain honest answer, and bring it to the Lawyer, and say, here I have brought my answer to the bill; this is not an answer (saith the Attorney) you must go to a Counsellor, &amp; get him to write an answer for you; why should I doe so, (saith the poor man) must I answer the bill, or the Counsellor? no saith the Attorney, you must answer the bill, but you must get a Counsellor to do it for you, for he will write it according to law, and put his hand to it; I can answer my self in truth (saith the poor man) &amp; put mine own hand to it; and why should not my own answer be taken with my own hand to it, I being the man that is commanded by the Law to answer; if you do not get your answer with the Counsellors hand to it (saith the Attorney, it will be a contempt. Then if the poor man for fear of a contempt do go to a Counsellor, then he must first give him his fee, and then if he be but an ordinarie Counsellor, it may be ten shillings may serve, but if he be a great one, which is gotten to the degree of the Coife, or a Sergeant at Law, then it will be more; and then the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellor will write an answer, and dress it finelie with many fine Lawyers words, many of which the poor man knoweth not what they mean, they being to him as a strange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and by his so doing he sets a new face upon the poor
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30444:21"/>mans answer; and so his answer becomes such a one as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Counsellor, whether it pleaseth the poor mans own conscience or not, for if the poor man be consciencious, &amp; would plead honestlie, according to the Scriptures, and the just and righteous laws of this Nation, then the Counsellor will not put his hand to it, except it please him, (so in very truth) it must be the Counsellors answer in the poor mans name, and if the poor man will not put in such an answer, it is called a contempt; &amp; when the Counsellor hath drawn such an answer in the poor mans name, then he must go to his Attorney, or some other man, and get him to ingross it in parchment, and then he must pay for that also; and when the poor man hath done all this, he must go before a Master if it be in Chancerie, or before a Baron if it be in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and then he must be sworn to that answer, &amp; give the Master or Baron that swears him 4 d. but if the poor man declares, that he cannot swear for conscience sake, because Christ hath commanded, <hi>swear not all,</hi> then neither Master nor Baron will take his answer, but chide him, and frown upon him (&amp; said Baron <hi>Nicholas</hi>) if you will not swear, we swear, and if you will not swear, you shall go to prison for a contempt: Shew me that law (saith the poor man) that commands me to swear to my answer. (said Baron <hi>Nicholas</hi>) we know a law, though you do not; tell me then when that law was made, &amp; by whom (saith the poor man) that I may read it, for the Law of <hi>England</hi> is to be read to the people four times a year in full countie, as appears by the 28 year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the first, &amp; the first chapter, and many other good laws, &amp; therefore I desire to know when that law was made, that commands me to swear to my answer; Get you gone sirrah (said Baron <hi>Nicholsa</hi>) I profess if you come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me again I will lay you by the heels.</p>
               <p>Then if the poor man, for fear of a contempt or prison, do swear to his answer, then saith his Attorney, here will be replication, and I must take a copie of it for you, &amp; you must give me eight pence a sheet for it; when the poor man reads it, he finds it an ill-favoured thing, saying, that the answer is altogether untrue, unjust, and insufficient in the law, then the poor man tels his Attorney (this is not true) this is our formalitie
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30444:22"/>(saith the Attorney;) then your formalities are lies (saith the poor man;) well, well, (saith the Attorney) now you must put in a Rejoynder to this Replication; what is that (saith the poor man?) give me money (saith the Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney) and I will put it in for you, you cannot do it your self; and many such like dirtie things (as these) he cals to the poor man for money for.</p>
               <p>After all this the poor man is served with another Writ, commanding the poor man to appear in his own person, to hear judgement, &amp; when the poor man hears his name cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, he answers, here I am; where is your Counsellor, saith the Judges? I am here my self (saith the poor man;) but you must have a Councellor to plead for you (saith the Judges) Is this cause mine, or is it a Councels (saith the poor man?) no it is your cause, saith the Judges and Lawyers; well then saith the poor man, if the cause be mine, then hear me, for the righteous Law of God, and the just law of <hi>England</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Judges to hear the poor as well as the rich, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out respect of persons, and so it doth not command you to hear the counsel only, but me, whose the cause is; if you will not have counsel your cause will suffer, saith the Judge; I am sure, saith the poor man, a Councellor cannot plead my cause, except he have instruction from me what to plead, and therefore if I am able to instruct a Counsellor what to plead, I am able to plead my cause my self, for greater is the teacher then he that is taught, &amp; therefore I say, I know my cause better then a Counsellor; but saith the Judge, you may be ignorant of the law for all this, and therefore you must have counsel: but saith the poor man, if I know my cause my self, as to matter of fact, you the Judges are to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form me, if I mistake in matter of law, for that end are you set there as Judges. But for all this if the poor man be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled, and be driven to put his cause into a Councels hand, then between the Counsel and the Judges, they can make the poor mans cause look with what face they please, &amp; the poor man shall have no more law, but just so much as they please to measure him out; and then then if the Counsellor that pleaded for him be but an ordinarie Counsellor, he will have 20 s. if not 30. &amp; if he be a Sergeant at Law, or Coife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30444:22"/>then 40 s. a fee. Then if the poor mans cause be cast, if it be matter of imprisonment, the poor man must go to prison, and then neither Attorney, nor Councel, nor any of them all will go to prison for him, nor give him his money again: in few words, here is the poor mans case, the poor man paies for all, and suffers for all, and the Lawyers goeth away with all, and the poor man must stand by and see himself rob'd of his birth-right.</p>
               <p>And now all sober people consider the poor mans case, if it be not against law &amp; reason to be compelled to come to a Court, &amp; when he comes must not do his own work himself for fear of contempts, as they cal them, but must hire other men to do it, whether he will or no, &amp; must pay them for it at a very high rate, giving them more money for one daies work, then he himself can get in ten, and if they spoil his work, yet they will not give him his money again; now is not this far worse then any manual occupation? as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if a man go to a Joyners shop, or the like, &amp; bid him make him a bedstead, and give him his money before-hand, if the Joyners tools be naught, &amp; he spoil it in making, yet the man will expect, as very well he may, that the Joyner shall make him a good bedstead, fit for his service, and stand to the loss of the bad one himself, or else give the man his money again; and if so, why should not the Lawyers trie the poor mans cause again at their own charge, till they make it hold, &amp; so shew themselves workmen of their trade, or else give the poor man all his money again, &amp; let him either seek better workmen, or do his work himself next time. And now I require of all, or any of you Judges or Lawyers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether there be any law in <hi>England,</hi> that cals it a contempt for a man to come into a Court with his hat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head? if there be, tell the poor man when that law was made, and by whom.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether there be any law in <hi>England</hi> that cals it a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt for a man to appear and answer in the court without an Attorney? if there be, tell the poor man when it was made, and by whom.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether there be any law in <hi>England,</hi> that cals it a contempt, for a man to write his own answer truly, and in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30444:23"/>plainness of speech, according to his own conscience, under his own hand, without the help or hand of any Counsel? if there be, tell the poor man when it was made, &amp; by whom.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether there be any law in <hi>England,</hi> that cals it a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, for not swearing to his answer, when as Christ hath commanded, <hi>swear not at all,</hi> &amp; in obedience to his command the poor man dare not do it for conscience sake; if there be such a law, tell the poor man when it was made, &amp; by whom.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether there be any law in <hi>England,</hi> that cals it a contempt for a man to plead his own cause in a court with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Counsellor? if there be such a law, tell the poor man when it was made, and by whom.</p>
               <p>If there be no such laws as I here querie, what have you done, O you Judges and Counsellors, &amp;c. to commit some poor men to prison for coming to the Courts at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands with their hats on, which God hath given them for a covering? &amp; what have you done, in committing many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poor men for contempts, as you call them, for want of answers? when as they came to you with answers in their hands, and would have given them you, and you would not receive them, because they could not swear for conscience sake, though they have declared their answers to be true, as in the fight of God, yet have you, or your ministers, put some of them in one prison, and some in another, in several parts of this Nation, and some in a dungeon neer twenty foot deep.</p>
               <p>O ye Judges of <hi>England:</hi> would you have such judgement measured unto you again, as you have measured unto these poor men? sure you would not.</p>
               <p>O ye chief Magistrates of <hi>Engl.</hi> who putteth such Judges in authority, and suffers them thus to oppress just men, whose consciences are so tender to the Lord; is this according to your promises and ingagements unto the Lord in the day of your distress? sure I am it is not; and therefore all you chief Magistrates &amp; Rulers in <hi>Engl.</hi> fear and dread before the Lord God, who will not be mocked, least he come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you unawares, and over-turn you, by the same arme and power, as he did them that are gone before you, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point you a hypocrites portion, for saying, and doing the contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30444:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>